When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
The liver is a crucial organ in the body,
playing a vital role in metabolism,
detoxification, digestion,
blood sugar regulation,
and vitamin storage.
Today we start with a story about the
liver damage caused by Herbalife supplements.
Herbalife is
a multi-billion-dollar,
multi-level
marketing supplement company
that was forced to pay
hundreds of millions of dollars
to settle charges of deception
and corrupt business practices.
It also holds the distinction
of being the dietary supplement
most frequently implicated
in injuring
the livers of consumers.
Herbal does not mean innocuous.
Cases of severe liver toxicity
associated
with Herbalife supplements
started to be published in 2007
around the world.
As the accompanying
editorial summarized,
there were 22 cases
of liver damage
following Herbalife intake
in the first two reports,
with two patients developing
fulminant liver failure
requiring liver transplantation.
Only one survived.
The editorial concluded
that this clearly shifts
the risk-benefit ratio
against its use.
Maybe it's contaminated
with chemicals or heavy metals,
maybe due to contamination
with a liver toxic bacteria
found in implicated products.
Additional reports
continued to be published,
followed by rebuttals
written by Herbalife
company representatives
questioning cause-and-effect.
No small task,
given that people were taking
up to 17 different
Herbalife products at one time.
So how strong is the evidence?
A key factor to look for
is re-challenge tests
or "positive re-exposure."
Did someone decide
to take the product again
after the initial
liver injury resolved,
and did their symptoms return
on re-challenge?
Based on stringent
causality assessment methods
like positive re-exposure tests,
cause-and-effect
is considered probable
for at least
a few Herbalife products.
They are such
a moving target, though,
with "hundreds of different
products marketed globally
in over 88 markets,
where in many cases
the formula is
unique to a region..."
Positive rechallenge cases
continue to be published,
confirming the toxic cause
of liver damage
from Herbalife products,
perhaps by triggering
an autoimmune reaction.
This fatal case
of a 24-year-old woman
was attributed
to Herbalife products,
which were evidently found
to contain heavy metals,
traces of a psychotropic
recreational agent,
and pathogenic bacteria.
The paper was subsequently
taken down for "legal reasons"
after legal threats
by Herbalife.
LiverTox is a federal initiative
between the National
Institutes of Health
and the National
Library of Medicine
to categorize the likelihood
that substances
can damage the liver,
all the way up to the highest
likelihood—Category A—
meaning it is a well-known,
well-described,
and well-reported
cause of liver damage.
And that's exactly
how it characterized
Herbalife supplements:
A well-established cause
of clinically apparent
liver injury.
In our next story,
we look at the dietary factors
that can contribute to liver disease.
In the documentary, Supersize Me, Morgan Spurlock
eats exclusively at McDonald's for a month,
and predictably his weight, blood
pressure, and cholesterol go up,
but so do his liver enzymes,
a sign his liver cells are dying and spilling
their contents into the bloodstream.
His one-man experiment was
actually formally replicated.
A group of men and women agreed to eat
two fast food meals a day for a month,
and most of their liver values started
out normal, under 30 here for men,
but within just one week,
most were out of whack,
a profound pathological
elevation in liver damage.
What's happening is NAFLD,
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease,
the next global epidemic.
Fatty deposits in the liver can result
in a disease spectrum —
from asymptomatic fat buildup,
to NASH, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis,
which can lead to liver
scarring and cirrhosis,
which can result in liver cancer,
liver failure, and death.
It's now the most common cause
of chronic liver disease in the U.S.,
affecting 70 million Americans —
that's like one in three adults.
And fast food is a great
way to bring it on,
since it's associated with the
intake of soft drinks and meat.
One can of soda a day may raise
the odds of fatty liver 45%,
and those eating the equivalent of 14
chicken nuggets worth of meat a day
have nearly triple the rates of fatty liver
compared to like seven nuggets or less.
It's been characterized as a tale of fat
and sugar, but evidently not all types of fat.
Those with fatty hepatitis ate
more animal fat and cholesterol,
and less plant fat, fiber, and
antioxidants, which may explain
why adherence to a Mediterranean-style
diet, characterized by high consumption
of foods such as fruits, vegetables,
whole grains, and beans
is associated with less severe
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease,
perhaps because of the anti-inflammatory
and antioxidant effects.
Maybe because of specific phytonutrients,
like the purple, red, blue anthocyanin
pigments in berries and grapes, and plums,
red cabbage, red onions, radicchio.
These anthocyanin-rich foods may be
promising for the prevention of fatty liver,
but that's mostly based
on Petri dish experiments.
There was one clinical trial that did find
that drinking a purple sweet potato
beverage seemed to successfully
dampen liver inflammation though.
A more plant-based diet may
also improve our microbiome,
the good bacteria in our gut. The
old adage, "we are what we eat"
may be changing to "we are
what our bacteria eat."
And when we eat fat, we may
facilitate the growth of bad bacteria,
which can release inflammatory
molecules that increase
the leakiness of our gut and
contribute to fatty liver disease.
Fatty liver disease can also be
caused by cholesterol overload.
The thought is that dietary cholesterol
found in eggs, meat, and dairy
oxidizes and then up-regulates
liver X receptor alpha,
which can up-regulate something
else called SREBP,
which can increase the
level of fat in the liver.
Cholesterol crystals alone cause
human white blood cells to spill out
inflammatory compounds, just
like uric acid crystals in gout.
That's what may be triggering the
progression of just plain fatty liver
into serious hepatitis,
the accumulation of sufficient
concentrations of free cholesterol
within fatty liver cells to cause
crystallization of the cholesterol-
one of several recent lines of evidence
suggesting that dietary cholesterol plays
an important role in the development
of fatty hepatitis, fatty liver inflammation.
In a study of 9,000 American
adults followed for 13 years,
they found a strong association
between dietary cholesterol intake
and hospitalization and death
from cirrhosis and liver cancer,
as dietary cholesterol can oxidize and
cause toxic and carcinogenic effects.
To limit the toxicity of excess
cholesterol derived from the diet,
the liver tries to rid itself of cholesterol
by dumping it into the bloodstream,
and so by measuring the
non-HDL cholesterol in the blood
one can predict the onset
of fatty liver disease.
If you subtract HDL from total cholesterol,
none of the hundreds of people
they followed with a value under
130 developed the disease.
Drug companies view non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease as a bonanza,
as is the case of any disease of
affluence, considering its already high
and raising prevalence, needing
continuous pharmacologic treatment.
But maybe it's as easy
as changing our diet,
avoiding sugary and
cholesterol-laden foods.
The unpalatable truth is that
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease
could almost be considered the
human equivalent of foie gras,
as we "force-feed" ourselves foods that
can result in serious health implications.
However, having such a buttery
texture in human livers
is not a delicacy to be enjoyed by
liver doctors in clinical practice
as it can have such
serious consequences.
Finally today,
did you know that cancer-
causing viruses in poultry
may explain increased risks of death
from liver and pancreatic cancers?
Here’s the story.
Thousands of Americans continue
to die from asbestos exposure
decades after many
uses were banned
because the cancers can
take years to show up.
We are now in the so-called third
wave of asbestos related disease.
The first wave was in
the asbestos miners,
which started in the 1920s.
The second phase
was in the workers—
the ship-builders and
construction workers
that used the stuff in
the 30s, 40s, and 50s.
Now as "buildings constructed
with asbestos"
"over the past six decades begin
to age and deteriorate”,
not only are
workers at risk,
but "Potential also exists for
serious environmental exposure"
"to asbestos among residents, tenants
and users of these buildings"
"such as school children, office workers,
maintenance workers, and the general public.”
The CDC, the American
Academy of Pediatrics,
and the EPA "have projected
that over the next 30 years"
"approximately 1,000 cases of
mesothelioma and lung cancer "
"will occur among persons
in the United States"
"exposed to asbestos in school
buildings as school children."
But it all started
with the workers.
As one internal industry
memo callously put it,
"If you've enjoyed a good life while working
with asbestos products why not die from it."
To see if something
is carcinogenic,
you study those who have
the most exposure.
That's how we learned
about the potential
cancer-causing
dangers of asbestos,
and that's how we're
learning about
the potential cancer-causing
dangers of poultry viruses.
For years I've talked about
the excess mortality
in poultry workers associated
with these wart-causing
chicken cancer viruses
that may be transmitted
to those in the general population
handling fresh or frozen chicken.
Last year I talked about the largest
study to date, at the time,
confirming the findings
of three other studies
“that workers in poultry slaughtering
and processing plants"
"have increased risk of
dying from certain cancers”,
and adding death
from penis cancer
to the risks linked
to poultry exposure.
That was looking at
20,000 poultry workers.
Well, we have yet another study,
looking at 30,000.
The purpose of
the study was to
"test the hypothesis that exposure
to poultry (cancer) viruses"
"that widely occurs occupationally
in poultry workers"
not to mention the
general population,
"may be associated with
increased risks of deaths"
"from liver and
pancreatic cancers."
They found that those
who slaughter chickens
have about 9 times the odds of both
pancreatic cancer and liver cancer.
Just to put this in context,
the most carefully studied risk
factor for pancreatic cancer,
one of our deadliest cancers,
is cigarette smoking.
Even if you smoke for more
than 50 years, though,
you only about double your
odds of pancreatic cancer.
Those that slaughter
poultry appear to have
nearly 9 times the odds.
For liver cancer,
it's more alcohol.
Those that consume more
than a four drinks a day
have triple odds of lung cancer,
whereas poultry slaughtering appears
to increase one's odds 9 fold.
There are diseases unique
to the meat industry,
like the newly described
"salami brusher's disease"
that affects those whose job
it is to wire brush off
the white mold that
naturally grows on salami,
for 8 hours a day,
but most diseases suffered by
meat workers are more universal.
The reason the connection
between asbestos and cancer
was so easy to
nail down is that
asbestos caused a particularly
unusual cancer,
which was virtually
unknown until there was
widespread asbestos mining
and industrial use.
But the pancreatic cancer one
might get from handling chicken,
is the same pancreatic cancer one
might get from smoking cigarettes,
so it's more difficult to tease out
a cause-and-effect relationship.
So don't expect to see
an asbestos-type ban
on Kentucky Fried Chicken
anytime soon.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.